Guide to the Gene Federico Papers, 1918-2003 and undated, bulk 1951-1991 RL.00383
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gene Federico papers
1918-2003 and undated bulk 1951-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Federico, Gene
RL.00383
20.5 Linear Feet
3800 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gene Federico Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003 and 2004.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1918 Feb. 6 Born in New York, NY
1936 Graduated Abraham Lincoln High School; Art Squad member; studied with Leon Friend, along with fellow students Alex Steinweiss, Seymour Chwast, and William Taubin
1939 Graduated from the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, NY; studied with Tom Benrimo
1939 Member of the Art Students League; studied with Howard Trafton and Herbert Bayer
1939-1940 Joined the Abbott Kimball Company, Art Department
1941 Joined the Art Department staff of the L. Bamberger Department Store
1941-1945 Served four years in the United States Army, stationed in the U.S., Europe, and North Africa; member of the 84th Engineer Camouflage Batallion, supervised graphics for Plans and Operations
1945-1946 Returned to the Abbott Kimball Company as Art Director
1946 Participated in the Four Veterans Exhibit at the A-D Gallery, along with fellow artists/designers Herbert Bender, Charles Egri, and Seymour Robins
1946-1947 Joined Fortune Magazine as Associate Art Director
1948-1951 Joined Grey Advertising as Art Director
1949 Became Instructor in Design at The Workshop School
1951-1954 Became Art Director at Doyle, Dane, Bernbach Advertising
1954-1959 Served as Art Director and Vice-President at Douglas D. Simon Advertising
1959-1966 Joined Benton & Bowles as Vice-President and Group Head
1966-1967 Joined Warwick & Legler Advertising
1967-1989 Founding partner of Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein
1980 Inducted into Art Director's Club Hall of Fame
1987 Received American Institute of Graphic Arts medal
1988 Became Creative Director at Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein; promoted to Vice-Chairman in April
1989-1991 Served as consultant with Brouillard Communications
1990 May 12 Received Honorary Doctorate of Fine Arts from The Parsons School of Design
1991 Retired as design consultant
1991-1999 Continued to work as freelance graphic designer; capstone to sixty-year career in advertising and graphic design
1999 Sept. 8 Died in Pound Ridge, NY
Collection Overview
The Gene Federico Papers span the years 1918-2003, with the bulk of the collection dating 1951-1991. The collection documents Federico's sixty years as a pioneering leader in advertising and graphic design, and contains materials from a variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, advertisements proofs and clippings, graphic design and printed materials, posters, sketches/sketchbooks, photographs, negatives, and videotapes. In addition to limited personal and biographical material, the collection primarily documents Federico's creative output as a graphic designer, art director, and advertising executive at agencies including Grey Advertising, Doyle Dane Bernbach, Douglas D. Simon, Benton & Bowles, Warwick & Legler, and as a principal at Lord Geller Federico Einstein; the collection has limited material relating to the specific agencies for which he worked. The collection also documents Federico's extensive freelance and exhibition work throughout his career (most notably the Love of Apples and 24-Page Book designs), in addition to his later consulting work for Brouillard Communications. Client advertisements and graphic design materials compose the majority of the collection. Significant clients represented include: Christian Dior; Elektra Records; Elizabeth Arden; Goldman Sachs; IBM; L'Aiglon Apparel; Lady Pepperell; Napier; The New Yorker; and Woman's Day. Though an art director throughout most of his career, Federico contributed significantly to the graphic design and typographical components of advertising. Through clear and innovative integration of design and typographical components, Federico pioneered the use of visual puns in advertisements, and emphasized clarity of message over design complexity. The collection will be of particular value to researchers interested in developments in print advertising and typographical design since World War II. The collection is organized into six series which focus on Federico's contributions to advertising and graphic design: Professional Files, Personal Files, Graphic Design, Advertising Campaigns, Photographs and Negatives, and Videocassettes.
The Professional Files Series includes business correspondence, professional writings, award/exhibit materials, press clippings and industry publications, in addition to limited files on the Art Directors Club of New York City and Lord Geller Federico Einstein. The Personal Files Series includes biographical and family materials; memorabilia documenting Federico's years as a student at Abraham Lincoln High School and Pratt Institute; World War II materials, including U.S. Army publications/posters produced by Federico and four sketchbooks; and original artwork (drawings, sketches, prints) not related to Federico's professional design and advertising work. The Graphic Design Series documents Federico's extensive graphic design work, including announcements and cards, book and record cover designs, calendars, design concepts, illustrations, letterhead, posters, transparencies, and typographic materials, as well as materials by other artists and designers. The Advertising Campaigns Series includes advertisement clippings and proofs, concepts and sketches, and client reports, representing over one hundred clients in a variety of industries. (Series contains a renowned example of Federico's use of visual puns: a 1953 Woman's Day advertisement - She's got to Go Out to get Woman's Day - which features a woman on a bicycle, the wheels of which form the Os in Go Out.) The Photographs and Negatives Series includes both black & white and color images of Federico's advertising and graphic design work, Federico and his associates in a business setting, and a limited selection of personal and family photographs. The Videocassettes Series includes seven videotapes of commercials, short films, and memorial tributes documenting Federico's career in graphic design and advertising. Large-format materials (clippings, proofs, sketches, posters) have been removed from their original series location and relocated to Oversize Materials.
Other materials related to this collection may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Competitive Advertisements Collection and Corporation Vertical Files. For materials relating specifically to the advertising agency Benton & Bowles, consult the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Advertisements and Archives. Materials relevant to Lord Geller Federico Einstein and advertising strategy may be found in the Arthur Einstein Papers. For materials relating to Brouillard Communications and Doyle Dane Bernbach Advertising, see the Thomas F. Garbett Papers. Materials relevant to IBM advertising may be found in the Edgar Hatcher Papers.
Commercial art -- United States; Commercial artists -- United States; Videocassettes; Graphic arts -- United States; Graphic artists -- United States; Sketches; Graphic design (Typography) -- United States; Photographs; Advertising -- Brand name products; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- Clothing and dress; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising -- United States; Advertising layout and typography; Advertising executives -- United States; Posters; Negatives (photographic); Sketchbooks; Proofs (printed matter); Federico, Gene, 1918-1999; Elizabeth Arden, Inc.; Goldman, Sachs & Co; Federico, Gene; Benton & Bowles; Elektra Records (Firm); Christian Dior, Inc.; Pepperell Manufacturing Company; International Business Machines Corporation; Brouillard Communications, Inc.; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; L'Aiglon Apparel, Inc.; Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein, Inc.
- Professional Files Series, 1951-1999 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains files related to Federico's work with the Art Directors Club from the 1950s through 1990s; industry publications, primarily in the field of graphic and typographic design; press clippings profiling Federico, his work, and employers/agencies; business correspondence; resumes and related documents outlining Federico's professional biography; files documenting Federico's role as a judge and recipient of industry awards and exhibits; writings within the fields of graphic design and advertising, by Federico and others; and limited office files for Lord Geller Federico Einstein. Of particular note is Federico's correspondence with artist/mentor Leon Friend, American design critic/journalist Steven Heller, and Martin Sorrell of the WPP Group. Series arranged alphabetically; correspondence arranged chronologically by year.
  - Art Directors Club (ADC) (Box 1)
    - ADC Hall of Fame
      - Awards and inductees, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Exhibit, 1973 (Box 1)
      - Program/Reception, 1980 (Box 1)
    - An Evening With One of the Best: Gene Federico, undated (Box 1)
    - Publications
      - adc (Journal of the Art Directors Club), 1990 Summer (Box 1)
      - ADC International Review
        - Volume 1 (Number 1-4), circa 1995-1996 (Box 1)
        - Volume 2 (Number 1-4), 1996 (Box 1)
      - Art Directors Club, Inc. Newsletter
        - 1979 Summer (Box 1)
        - 1993 Summer (excerpt: computers in advertising) (Box 1)
      - Magazine of the Art Directors Club, 1966 Dec. (Box 1)
      - Madison Avenue: The Century's Greatest Advertising: quote release form, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Awards and exhibits
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts (AIGA)
      - Design and printing for commerce and Fifty advertisements of the Year exhibition
        - Fourteenth Annual Exhibition, 1956 (Box 1)
        - Fifteenth Annual Exhibition, 1957 (Box 1)
      - Print Ads of the Year exhibition notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Conference brochures - Various, 1971, 1979 and 1987 (Box 1)
    - Exhibition programs, 1947, 1990 and undated (Box 1)
    - Honorary Doctorate: Parsons School of Design (photocopy), 1990 May 12 (Box 1)
    - Image 1971 Conference, Winston-Salem, NC, 1972 Jan. (Box 1)
    - Japanese Graphic Idea Exhibition: Judge's comments, 1981 (Box 1)
    - New York City School Volunteer Program: Honor Roll of distinguished alumni, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Pioneer-Moss contest, 1968 and undated (Box 1)
    - Type Directors Club of New York
      - Second Annual Awards, 1956 (Box 1)
      - Third Annual Awards, 1957 (Box 1)
      - Fourth Annual Awards, 1958 (Box 1)
      - Fifth Annual Awards, 1959 (Box 1)
      - Type Directors Club Medal - Awarded to Gene Federico (invitation designed by daughter Gina Federico), 1991 (Box 1)
      - Typography-U.S.A. forum, 1959 Apr. (Box 1)
    - Various, 1988 and 1992 (Box 1)
      [Contains materials on Federico's AIGA Medal and Fashion Institute Of Technology event, Gene Federico: Profile of an American Master.]
  - Business cards/contacts - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts (AIGA) Medal: LGFE congratulations, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Art Directors Club, 1949 and 1978 (Box 1)
    - Friend, Leon, 1957 Jan. 6 (Box 1)
    - Heller, Steven, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - The New Yorker, 1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Postcards, 1966 Apr. (Box 1)
    - The Saturday Evening Post: The Girl Who Hated Men illustration, 1962 (Box 1)
      [Benton & Bowles / Saturday Evening Post letters congratulating Federico; illustration is in Graphic Design Series: Illustrations, Saturday Evening Post, 1962.]
    - Sorrell, Martin, 1989-1999 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1999 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Federico portraits (caricature, photomechanical print), 1979 and 1987 (Box 1)
    [Contains signed print by famed New York Times artist/caricaturist Al Hirschfeld.]
  - Financial Papers, 1961-1963, 1993 and undated (Box 1)
  - Industry publications
    - American Artist: Gene Federico: designer into art director, 1956 Dec. (Box 1)
    - AAAA Newsletter (American Association of Advertising Agencies), 1987 (Box 1)
    - American Institute of Graphic Arts (AIGA): Fifteenth Annual Exhibition
      - AIGA Journal, 1951 (Box 1)
      - aiga NY!: Bulletin #18, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Art Direction
      - 1957 Dec.: Jo Collins campaign captions (Box 1)
      - 1958 Mar.: What's New... What's Best in Creative Advertising (Disraeli/Container Corporation advertisement) (Box 1)
    - Art Students League of New York catalog (Howard Trafton article), undated (Box 1)
    - Benton & Bowles Bulletin, 1960 Mar. (Box 1)
    - A Comparison of the Creative Philosophies of Doyle Dane Bernbach and Ogilvy & Mather, undated (Box 1)
    - Designer's Guide: Crafting Advertising Typography (with Gene Federico), 1990 (Box 1)
    - Exciting design sparks type exhibition, circa 1958 (Box 1)
    - Friem's Four Pages (A.I. Friedman, Inc.): Presenting Gene Federico, 1951 Apr. (Box 1)
    - Gebrauchsgraphik: International Advertising Art (Federico article), 1959 June (Box 1)
    - Graphics: New York, 1976 Feb. (Box 1)
    - High Quality (HQ) magazine ( Cryptographics and other articles) (Box 2)
      - 1986 May (Box 2)
      - 1989 Jan. (Box 2)
      - 1994 Mar. (Box 2)
    - League Quarterly: An Art Director Speaks, 1950 Spring (Box 2)
    - Madison Avenue: Lord, Geller, Federico, and Partners article, 1971 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Media Decisions: Creative's message to media, 1977 July (Box 2)
    - Pratt Reports, 1979 Summer (Box 2)
    - Type Talks: The Art of Mixing Typefaces: A visual demonstration by Gene Federico, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein
    - Employee list, 1988 (Box 2)
    - LGFE, Inc. Today memoranda: WPP/LGFE lawsuit and settlement, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Press clippings
    - On Federico
      - Daily News Magazine: The Camera '90: Ultimate Yearbook, NYC's Most Famous High School Grads, 1990 June 17 (Box 2)
      - Esquire magazine: 100 Best People in the World, 1965 Aug. (Box 2)
      - Il Manifesto: Napoli poster design article, 1986 Oct. 18 (Box 2)
        [Italian language newspaper, contents in Italian.]
      - The New York Times Magazine: Report on Men's Wear: An Art Director's Eye for Clothes, 1976 Sept. 19 (Box 2)
      - Pound Ridge Review: Gene and Helen Federico, Life of Shared Achievements, 1992 Oct. 15 (Box 2)
      - Wall Street Journal: Creative Leaders insert, 1981-1987 (Box 2)
      - Woman's Day profile, undated (Box 2)
      - Various
        - 1960, 1969-1979 and undated (Box 2)
        - 1981-1989 (Box 2)
        - 1990-1992, 1996 and undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1959-1997 and undated (Box 2)
  - Professional biography
    - Biography and resumes, 1975, 1989-1999 and undated (Box 2)
    - Obituary/memorial (by Steven Heller), 1999 Sept. 10 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - By Federico
      - Artist/designer profiles
        - On Aaron Burns (memorial), 1991 (Box 2)
        - On Leon Friend, 1976, 1987 (Box 2)
          [Leon Friend was an art teacher at Abraham Lincoln High School, director of the Art Squad, and one of Federico's most important early mentors.]
        - On Amil Gargano, 1996 Oct. 25 (Box 2)
        - On Bruno Monguzzi, 1991 Dec. 10 (Box 2)
      - Electrifying(drafts), undated (Box 2)
      - Tschichold vs. Kitch (as Chairman and Juror of TDC Exhibition), undated (Box 2)
      - Various (on design), 1960, 1971 and undated (Box 2)
    - By Others
      - Kyla Gill, Gene Federico: A Profile of the World Renowned Advertising Designer, 1999 (Box 2)
      - Steven Heller article/spreads, Gene Federico: An Art Director's Art Director, undated (Box 2)
      - Lawrence Miller: Federico career tribute, undated (Box 2)
      - Paul Rand article: Gene and Helen Federico, Graphis, circa 1950s (Box 2)
        [Full text of article appears in English, German, and French language translations.]
      - Martin Sorrell: Beans and pearls, D & AD President's Lecture, 1996 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Interviews, 1990 and undated (Box 2)
- Personal Files Series, 1918-2003 and undated, bulk circa 1940s-1999
  Consists primarily of Federico's personal correspondence with friends and family, memorabilia from Abraham Lincoln High School and Pratt Institute, family memorabilia, and materials documenting his World War II service. Also includes original artwork (sketches, drawings, watercolors) by Gene and Helen Federico not related to their professional design or advertising work. Of particular note are four sketchbooks from World War II, composed of notes, sketches, designs, and clippings. Arranged alphabetically by folder title, chronologically therein when appropriate.
  [Many original items in this series - sketchbooks and personal documents - have been photocopied and returned to the donor.]
  - Birth certificate/travel documents 1918, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - 1976-1989 (Box 2)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 2)
      - 1996-1998 (Box 2)
      - undated (Box 2)
    - Helen Federico (e-mail), 2000-2003 (Box 2)
    - Labchik Kampinsky, undated (Box 2)
  - Family memorabilia, 1959-2002 and undated (Box 2)
  - Abraham Lincoln High School
    - Graduation material (and copies), 1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Alumni News, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Silver anniversary luncheon, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Trafton lecture announcement, undated (Box 2)
  - Memorial service, 1999 (Box 2)
  - The New York Times (front page), 1918 Feb. 6 (Box 2)
    [Photocopy of front page from the day Federico was born.]
  - Original artwork
    - Federico drawings, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
    - Monotint etching, undated (Box 2)
    - Paintings and collages, undated (Box 2)
    - San Valentio, Abruzzi drawing (Gene and Helen Federico), 1971 (Box 2)
    - Sketches, 1977 and undated (Box 2)
    - Various (pigeon collage, siamese twins, musicians), 1940 and undated (Box 2)
  - Pratt Grad newsletter, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    [Spring 1991 issue lists Federico as the recipient of 1990 Alumni Achievement award. See p.10.]
  - World War II materials
    - Identification and army documents, 1941-1945 and undated (Box 2)
    - Posters
      - Conceal your shadow... as well as yourself, 1942 (Box 2)
        [Folder removed to Oversize Materials, Box OV2.]
      - Peace poster, 1944 (Box 2)
    - 7th Army Railroad Bridge booklet, circa 1941-1945
      - Originals (Box 2)
      - Color photocopy (Box 2)
    - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 2)
      [Some items removed to Oversize Box OV1.]
    - V-mail (correspondence), 1943-1944 and undated (Box 2)
- Graphic Design Series, 1934-2002 and undated, bulk 1940-1997
  Contains a wide variety of original graphic design materials: announcements for exhibits and awards; business and family cards, including the Federico family holiday cards from the late 1940s through early 1990s; calendars; cover designs for book jackets, record sleeves, and magazines; illustrations (featured in magazines); letterhead and corporate logo designs; posters; transparencies; and typographic designs and research. In addition to completed printed designs and final proofs, series includes preliminary concepts, sketches, and design components. Of particular note is the Additional designs grouping, which includes Federico's most famous designs not commissioned by a specific client: Love of Apples, cone and sphere, 24-page booklet. Also includes limited designs by other artists and designers, including Tom Benrimo and Andy Warhol. Arranged alphabetically within two groupings, designs by Federico and designs by others.
  - By Federico
    - Additional designs (Box 3)
      - American Institute of Graphic Arts (awards, exhibits), 1951-1965 and undated (Box 3)
      - Art Director's Club
        - Creativity brochure/Third Communication Conference, 1958 (Box 3)
        - 39th Annual Exhibition (entries, awards, medals), 1959-1960 and undated (Box 3)
      - Art and Illustration (for Chris Collins?), hand/cube in red paint, undated (Box 3)
      - Cheek to Cheek, circa 1965 (Box 3)
      - Cryptographics, undated (Box 3)
      - Hiram Halle Memorial Library - Pound Ridge, New York (Pro-bono work), 1989-1994 and undated (Box 3)
      - Love of Apples (booklet and prints), undated (Box 3)
      - Lundy wines (Box 3)
        [Designs completed by Federico in high school.]
      - My Message is a Simple One design, undated (Box 3)
      - N The Big Inning design (In the Beginning), 1985 (Box 3)
      - Push Pin Graphic design, 1978 and undated (Box 3)
      - Silver cone/cylinder design, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Sugarbush Valley Box, undated (Box 3)
      - Tokyo & Gene Federico: AGI Congress in Tokyo, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Type Directors Club award, 1959 (Box 3)
      - Wall clock design, 1986 (Box 3)
      - 24-Page Book, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Announcements/cards (Box 4)
      - American Institute of Graphic Arts (awards/exhibits), 1951-1965 and undated (Box 4)
      - Art Director's Club
        - Call for Arms contest and exhibit (cosponsored with Pioneer-Moss), undated (Box 4)
        - 39th Annual Exhibition (entries, awards, medals) 1959-1960 and undated (Box 4)
      - Art/Film exhibits
        - Art Squad (A-D Gallery), 1947 and undated (Box 4)
        - Cinema 16, 1949, 1951-1956, 1967 and undated (Box 4)
        - Four Veterans exhibit (A-D Gallery), 1946 (Box 4)
        - Greetings exhibit: Museum of Modern Art, 1966 (Box 4)
        - Various, 1947 and circa 1968 (Box 4)
      - Birth Announcements, 1950 and 1984 (Box 4)
      - Birthdays, 1976, 1979 and undated (Box 4)
      - Holiday Cards
        - Business
          - Architectural Forum/ Fortune, 1947 and undated (Box 4)
          - Lord Geller Federico, Inc. (design by Helen Federico), 1978 (Box 4)
          - Lord Geller Federico Einstein, undated (Box 4)
        - Personal
          - Federico family, 1943-1998 and undated (Box 4)
          - Helen/Gene Federico (Valentines/Birthdays), 1941, 1996 and undated (Box 4)
          - Merry Cuesta.. ., undated (Box 4)
      - Hotel Pierce Barber Shop (new manager announcement), 1941 (Box 4)
      - Moved - Various, undated (Box 4)
      - Toni Ficalora Studio, undated (Box 4)
      - Wedding invitation (Gene and Helen Federico), 1942 June (Box 4)
      - Various, 1948-1951 and undated (Box 4)
    - Calendars
      - Basil Pizza design, 1997 (Box 4)
      - DC & A, undated (Box 4)
        [Features designs by Gene Federico, Saul Bass and Seymour Chwast, among others.]
      - PM Typography, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - SPER (Italian), 1988 (Box 4)
      - T & H Calendar Review (Tileston & Hollingsworth), 1961 (Box 4)
    - Client catalogs/brochures
      - Abbott Kimball Co. Inc.: Publicity brochure, 1938 (Box 4)
        [Includes handwritten note from Federico to Steve (Heller?), describing the item as a vintage piece and the last one. According to note, brochure appeared in the Art Director's Club show of 1938.]
      - Art Director's Club: Creativity brochure/Third Communication Conference, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Jo Collins: every season is a Jo Collins season brochure, undated (Box 4)